Abhishek Mittal

■ amittal1311@gmail.com | 🖥 +1 (514) 464-5855 | 🞧 GitHub | 🛅 LinkedIn | 🔗 Portfolio

Summary

Bilingual **Software Engineer (English & French)**, bringing over 4+ years of experience centered on **Backend Development**, **Frontend Design**, and **Cloud Technologies**. Detail and result-oriented, committed to deadlines and proactive approaches for reliability and scalability, seeking an opportunity to actively contribute towards company success.

Education

Concordia University

Montreal, Canada

Master of Science in Applied Computer Science

2021 - 2023

Chitkara University

Himachal Pradesh, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science

2016 - 2020

Work Experience

Software Engineer

Montreal, Canada May 2023 - Present

DigiRovers Solutions

- Designed and implemented scalable **RESTful APIs** using **Java**, **Spring Boot** and **Node.js** in a microservices-based architecture, to support marketing automation and customer data processing.
- Integrated third-party APIs including Mailchimp, Google Ads, and Facebook Ads for automated marketing workflows.
- Optimized the system by resolving client defects and adding features through logic improvements and refactoring with lambdas and streams, reducing bug reports by 24% and increasing efficiency by 15%.
- Applied essential enhancements using **JWT** and **OAuth 2.0**, to strengthen security measures and eliminate potential vulnerabilities.

Software Developer

Goa, India

Rubiq Solutions

Sept 2019 - July 2021

- Led the design and development of microservices applications, generating \$1.3 million, using **Java**, **Spring Boot**, **AWS**, **React**, and **NodeJS**.
- Increased system efficiency by 30% by designing scalable APIs with **Spring Boot**, **AWS Lambda**, and **other AWS technologies**, serving thousands of daily requests.
- Optimized containerization and deployment with **Docker** and **Kubernetes**, reducing deployment time by 30% and improving scaling efficiency by 20%.
- Applied **Agile Methodologies** including CI/CD, pull requests, code reviews, and testing (unit, load, stress and integration tests).

Software Engineer Intern

Chandigarh, India May 2019 - Aug 2019

Kabera Global Technologies

- Implemented a messaging architecture with Kafka, improving microservices communication by 20%.
- Developed a secure messaging feature using **NodeJS** and **WebSocket**, enabling real-time communication.
- Refactored unit tests with **JUnit** and **Mockito**, increasing code quality by 28%.
- Contributed to code reviews, reducing page load times by 15% and documented processes for efficient knowledge transfer.

Projects

Apache Kafka Clone | Java, TCP Sockets, ByteBuffer

Built a Kafka broker clone handling metadata, message publishing, and topic message retrieval. Achieved 10,000 messages per second with sub-15ms latency for 95% of requests, demonstrating scalability and concurrency handling.

- Career Services Platform | Java, Spring Boot, PostgreSQL, React, NodeJS
 Led the development of a robust platform enabling employers to post job listings seamlessly, and candidates to browse and apply, capable of supporting 500+ simultaneous postings, accommodating 10,000+ active profiles, and handle 1000+ applications monthly.
- Plagiarism Detection Program | Java, Dynamic Programming, Eclipse IDE
 Designed a Java-based plagiarism detection program for source code files and text documents, achieving a 94% success rate in identifying instances of plagiarism. The program supports files with sizes up to 25MB, ensuring comprehensive coverage and accuracy.

Skills

Programming Languages: Java, JavaScript, C, C++, Python, SQL

Technologies & Tools: Spring, AWS, React, NodeJS, Apache Kafka, Docker, Kubernetes, Git, Jenkins, Figma

Databases: MongoDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL

Miscellaneous: Jira, JUnit, Mockito, Postman, Design Patterns, Agile/Waterfall Development, Microservices, Unit Testing, CI/CD, TDD, SDLC, REST, XML, JSON, MVC